Aaron Bohrod Papers
Aaron Bohrod Papers
1932-1963
Bohrod, Aaron.
3.75 linear ft.
Correspondence (1932-1963) with family, art organizations and associations, educational institutions, galleries and museums, patrons, and fellow artists; 3 original sketches; manuscript articles, critiques, notes, reviews, speeches; 2 lists of paintings, with descriptions and some prices; and a small amount of memorabilia. Correspondence with Ivan Albright, American Artists Group, Associated American Artists, Will Barnet, Cameron Booth, David Breger, Howard Cook, Adolf Dehn, August Derleth, Federal Art Project, Frank Getlein, Moss Hart, Kaj Klitgaard, Georges Schreiber, Lawrence Beall Smith, Raphael Soyer, Frederic Taubes, U.S. Dept. of the Treasury, U.S. War Office, Grant Wood, and many others.
148857
Biographical History
American realist painter (1907-1992). Participant in the Federal Art Project and the U.S. Army War Unit's project on the pictorial history of World War II.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Spanning 1932 to 1963, the Aaron Bohrod Papers comprises correspondence, artwork, writings, and memorabilia of the American realist painter and art educator (1907-1992). The collection focuses on the professional career, rather than the personal life, of the Chicago-born artist who taught for more than two decades at the University of Wisconsin.
Documenting Bohrod's participation in the U. S. Army War Unit's project on the pictorial history of World War II, Family Correspondence (Box 1) consists almost entirely of Bohrod's letters from the South Pacific to his wife Ruth and son Mark. A number of later family letters were written from Europe during Bohrod's assisgnment as artist correspondent for Life magazine.
Incoming letters with some outgoing holograph drafts and typescript carbons constitute the Correspondence-Subject Files (Boxes 2-8), which forms the bulk of the collection. Correspondents include art critics (John Canaday, Emily Genauer, Frank Getlein, Eleanor Jewett); authors (August Derleth, Albert Halper, Moss Hart, Gwendolen Haste); cartoonists (David and Irv Breger); ceramist F. Carlton Ball; entertainers (Edward G. Robinson, Meredith Wilson); and patrons (Orville Bulman, Edward C. Burman, Nathan Cummings, Arthur Fleischman, Lawrence A. Fleischman, Albert Hydeman, William J. Poplack, W. A. Sheaffer, Helene Tash, Charles D. Tenney). Among fellow painters, correspondence which is of greatest depth and duration includes that of Will Barnet, Cameron Booth, Howard Cook, Adolf Dehn, Kaj Klitgaard, Georges Schreiber, Samuel Schwartz, Burnett Shryock, Lawrence Beall Smith, Raphael Soyer, Frederic Taubes, Stuyvesant Van Veen, and Grant Wood. Other artist correspondents include Ivan and Malvin Albright, Minna Citron, Irvin Cowen, Stuart Davis, Thomas Dietrich, Ernest Fiene, Joseph Hirsch, Edward Hopper, Leon Kroll, Henry Lee McFee, Eugene Speicher, and A. Reid Winsey.
Organizational correspondence encompasses that with artists' associations (American Artists Group, Associated American Artists); educational institutions (Ball State Teachers College, DePauw University, Indiana University, Iowa State Teachers College, Lawrence College, Southern Illinois University, University of Wisconsin); galleries (Grand Central Art Galleries, Increase Robinson Gallery, Milch Galleries, Frank J. Oehlschlager Galleries, Frank K. M. Rehn); museums (Art Institute of Chicago, Butler Institute of American Art, Carnegie Institute, Detroit Institute of Arts, Los Angeles County Museum, Metropolitan Museum of Art, Milwaukee Art Institute, Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, Whitney Museum of American Art); and publications to which Bohrod contributed (Chicago Tribune, Esquire, Family Circle, Fortune, Holiday, Life, Look, Time). Materials relating to the Federal Art Project and the U.S. Treasury and War Departments illustrate the relationship between government and the artist.
The remainder of the collection, Artwork, Writings, and Memorabilia (Box 8) includes three original sketches and a few reproductions of Bohrod's work; notes, manuscripts, and some published articles, book reviews, speeches, and statements on art, as well as the manuscript for A Pottery Sketchbook; and two lists of paintings with descriptions and some prices.
Related Material
See also the following:
Associated American Artists Records
Dave Breger Papers
Minna Citron Papers
Howard Norton Cook Papers
Richard A. Florsheim Papers
Kaj Klitgaard Papers
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Albright, Ivan, 1897-1983.; Barnet, Will, 1911-2012.; Bohrod, Aaron.; Booth, Cameron, 1892-1980.; Breger, David, 1908-; Citron, Minna, 1896-1991.; Cook, Howard Norton, 1901-1980.; Dehn, Adolf, 1895-1968.; Derleth, August.; Florsheim, Richard A., 1916-1979.; Getlein, Frank.; Hart, Moss, 1904-1961.; Klitgaard, Kaj.; Schreiber, Georges, 1904-; Smith, Lawrence Beall, 1909-; Soyer, Raphael, 1899-1987.; Taubes, Frederic, 1900-1981.; Wood, Grant, 1891-1942.; American Artists Group.; Associated American Artists.; Federal Art Project.; United States. -- Department of the Treasury.; United States. -- War Department.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Artists -- Societies, etc.; Federal aid to the arts -- United States.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Realism in art.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Art and the war.; Articles.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Reviews (documents); Sketches.; Speeches (documents); Artists.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Aaron Bohrod, 1963.
Inventory
- Family Correspondence
  - Bohrod, Milton (brother), 1958; 1961 (Box 1)
  - Bohrod, Ruth (wife), 1939; 1943-1946; 1955; 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Bohrod, Mark (son), 1943-1945 (Box 1)
- Correspondence-Subject Files
  - A
    - A (misc), 1 folder (Box 2)
    - Adams, Jean Crawford, undated (Box 2)
    - Albright, Ivan, undated (Box 2)
    - Albright, Malvin, 1942; 1943 (Box 2)
    - American Art Research Council, 1943 (Box 2)
    - American Artist, 1953; 1958 (Box 2)
    - American Artists Group, Inc., 1939-1942; 1962 (Box 2)
    - American Federation of Arts, 1934; 1943,; 1955 (Box 2)
    - Anderson, Walter and Marguerite, 1942; undated (Box 2)
    - Art Association of Indianapolis, Indiana, 1949; 1952-1959 (Box 2)
    - Art Institute of Chicago, 1932-1945; 1958 (Box 2)
    - Associated American Artists, 1937-1947; 9 folders of 18 (Box 2)
    - Associated American Artists, 1948-1958; undated; 9 folders of 18 (Box 3)
    - Associated Magazine Contributors, Inc., 1946-1947 (Box 3)
    - Atlanta Art Association, 1954-1958 (Box 3)
  - B
    - B (misc), 1 folder (Box 3)
    - Baldinger, Wallace, 1937 (Box 3)
    - Ball, F. Carlton, undated (Box 3)
    - Ball State Teachers College, 1949-1956 (Box 3)
    - Barnet, Will, 1939-1942 (Box 3)
    - Barto, Emily, 1952 (Box 3)
    - Bates, Kenneth Francis, 1959 (Box 3)
    - Bekker, David, 1942 (Box 3)
    - Beloit College, 1950 (Box 3)
    - Benton, Rita P. (Mrs. Thomas Hart Benton), 1960 (Box 3)
    - [John Nelson] Bergstrom Art Center and Museum, 1959-1961 (Box 3)
    - Best Articles & Stories, 1960-1961 (Box 3)
    - Bethers, Ray, 1950; undated (Box 3)
    - Blanch, Arnold, 1945 (Box 4)
    - Bocour, Leonard, 1959 (Box 4)
    - Boni, Charles, See Living American Art, Inc.
    - Booth, Cameron, 1938-1942 (Box 4)
    - Breger, David, 1937; 1940-1945,; 1954,; 1960,; undated (Box 4)
    - Breger, Irv, 1938; undated (Box 4)
    - Britton, Edgar, 1942 (Box 4)
    - Brook, Alexander, 1935 (Box 4)
    - Brown, Ethel Crouch, 1941; undated (Box 4)
    - Brown, Isidore and Gladys, 1959-1961 (Box 4)
    - Bulman, Orville, undated (Box 4)
    - Burg, Copeland Charles, 1937; 1942 (Box 4)
    - Burkhart, Robert, 1956; 1961 (Box 4)
    - Burman, Edward C., 1941-1942 (Box 4)
    - Butler Institute of American Art (Youngstown, Ohio), 1942; 1957-1961 (Box 4)
  - C
    - C (misc), 1 folder (Box 4)
    - California Water Color Society, 1940-1942 (Box 4)
    - Canaday, John, 1961 (Box 4)
    - Carnegie Corporation, 1940-1943 (Box 4)
    - Carnegie Institute, 1936-1949; undated (Box 4)
    - Ceramics Monthly, 1953-1959; undated (Box 4)
    - Chaliapin, Boris, 1954 (Box 4)
    - Chapin, Francis and Vivian, 1953; 1959-1961,; undated (Box 4)
    - Chidsey, G. Alan, 1940; undated (Box 4)
    - Chicago Daily News, 1935-1939 (Box 4)
    - Chicago Tribune, 1948; 1959-1963,; undated (Box 4)
    - Church, C. Howard, 1946 (Box 4)
    - Citron, Minna, 1941; undated (Box 4)
    - Cole, Sylvan, 1952 (Box 4)
    - Coler, Stella, 1961 (Box 4)
    - Cook, Howard, 1943 (Box 4)
    - Corcoran Gallery of Art (Washington, D.C.), 1943 (Box 4)
    - Coronet Magazine, 1937; 1938 (Box 4)
    - Cowen, Irvin, 1961 (Box 4)
    - Cox, John Rogers, See Swope Art Gallery (Terre Haute, Ind.)
    - Cromie, Robert, See Chicago Tribune
    - Cummings, Nathan, 1947-1961 (Box 4)
    - Cunningham, Marion, 1943 (Box 4)
  - D
    - D (misc), 1 folder (Box 4)
    - Davis, Gladys Rockmore, undated (Box 4)
    - Davis, Stuart, 1935 (Box 4)
    - Dehn, Adolf, 1945; 1953-1960,; undated (Box 4)
    - DePauw University, 1957-1959; undated (Box 4)
    - Derleth, August, 1954 (Box 4)
    - Detroit Institute of Arts, 1952-1957; undated (Box 4)
    - Dietrich, Thomas, 1950; 1958-1959 (Box 4)
    - Downtown Gallery (New York, N.Y.), 1933-1934 (Box 4)
    - Duschnes, Philip C., 1941-1946 (Box 4)
  - E
    - E (misc), 1 folder (Box 4)
    - Ely, Frances, undated (Box 4)
    - Encyclopaedia Britannica, 1944-1946; 1950,; 1958 (Box 4)
    - Endicott, Robert R., 1954-1957 (Box 4)
    - Engle, Harry, 1941; undated (Box 4)
    - Esquire, 1940-1943; 1955 (Box 4)
  - F
    - F (misc), 1 folder (Box 4)
    - Falls Civic Art Center, See Richard, Jack
    - Family Circle Magazine, See Endicott, Robert R.
    - Farrar & Rinehart, 1940-1942 (Box 4)
    - Federal Art Project, 1935-1936 (Box 5)
    - Fiene, Ernest, 1942; 1956 (Box 5)
    - Findlay Galleries Inc., 1962 (Box 5)
    - Fleischman, Arthur, 1959-1960 (Box 5)
    - Fleischman, Lawrence A. and Barbara, 1956-1959; undated (Box 5)
    - Florsheim, Richard A., 1958; undated (Box 5)
    - Ford Foundation, 1958-1959 (Box 5)
    - Fortune, 1938-1949 (Box 5)
    - Fracassini, Silvio Carl, 1951 (Box 5)
    - Fredenthal, David, undated (Box 5)
  - G
    - G (misc), 1 folder (Box 5)
    - [Leon] Garland Foundation, Inc., 1943; 1952 (Box 5)
    - Geis, Bernard, 1937-1943; undated (Box 5)
    - Genauer, Emily, 1951; 1955 (Box 5)
    - Getlein, Frank, 1961; undated (Box 5)
    - Gimbel Brothers, 1948-1951 (Box 5)
    - Glasell, Criss, 1950 (Box 5)
    - Goldberg, Sidney, See Lawrence, Sidney
    - Golden Gate International Exposition, 1938-1939 (Box 5)
    - Grand Central Art Galleries, 1943; 1956-1958 (Box 5)
    - Greenburg, Samuel, 1956 (Box 5)
    - Greenwood, Marion, 1957; 1961 (Box 5)
    - Griffen, Davenport, 1933-1934; undated (Box 5)
    - Grigore, Julius and Doris, 1959-1961 (Box 5)
    - Gross, Earl, See Stevens, Gross Studios, Inc. (Chicago, Ill.)
    - Groth, John, undated (Box 5)
    - [John Simon] Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, 1935-1938 (Box 5)
  - H
    - H (misc), 1 folder (Box 5)
    - Halper, Albert, 1952 (Box 5)
    - Halpert, Edith, See Downtown Gallery (New York, N.Y.)
    - Hannon, James F., 1961 (Box 5)
    - Hart, Moss, 1940-1941 (Box 5)
    - Hartford, Huntington, 1956-1959 (Box 5)
    - Hartl, Leon, 1960 (Box 5)
    - Haste, Gwendolen, 1939 (Box 5)
    - Head, Lois, 1942 (Box 5)
    - [John] Herron Art Institute (Indianapolis, Ind.), See Art Association of Indianapolis, Indiana
    - Hirsch, Joseph, 1958 (Box 5)
    - Hodgell, Robert, 1949 (Box 5)
    - Hoffman, Bernie, 1960-1961 (Box 5)
    - Holiday, 1950-1951 (Box 5)
    - [Henry] Holt and Company, Inc., 1952-1953 (Box 5)
    - Hopper, Edward, 1939 (Box 5)
    - Hughes, Odien, See Nu-Art Engraving Company
    - Hydeman, Albert L., 1950-1954; undated (Box 5)
  - I
    - I (misc), 1 folder (Box 5)
    - Illinois State Fair, 1950-1954 (Box 5)
    - Indiana University, 1940-1944 (Box 5)
    - Iowa State Teachers College, 1956 (Box 5)
    - Irving Galleries Incorporated (Milwaukee, Wis.), 1961-1962 (Box 5)
  - J
    - J (misc), 1 folder (Box 5)
    - Jewell, Edward Alden, 1935-1939 (Box 5)
    - Jewett, Eleanor, 1955; undated (Box 5)
  - K
    - K (misc), 1 folder (Box 5)
    - Kaufmann, Edgar, undated (Box 5)
    - Kent, Norman, See American Artist
    - Klitgaard, Kaj, 1938-1941 (Box 5)
    - Krentzin, Earl, 1961; undated (Box 5)
    - Kroll, Leon, 1950; 1951,; undated (Box 5)
    - Kuniyoshi, Yasuo, 1937; 1947 (Box 5)
  - L
    - L (misc), 1 folder (Box 5)
    - Lahey, Richard, 1943 (Box 5)
    - Lankes, Julius J., 1942 (Box 5)
    - Lawrence, Sidney, 1938; 1940 (Box 5)
    - Lawrence College (Appleton, Wis.), 1950-1959 (Box 5)
    - Lax, David, undated (Box 5)
    - Levin, Meyer, undated (Box 5)
    - Life, 1939-1961; undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Eli Lilly and Company, 1959-1961 (Box 6)
    - Lion, Stephan, 1957-1958 (Box 6)
    - Living American Art, Inc., 1936-1940 (Box 6)
    - Longman, Lester D., See Parnassus
    - Look, 1951-1961; undated (Box 6)
    - Lorant, Stefan, 1956; 1960 (Box 6)
    - Los Angeles County Museum, 1934-1944 (Box 6)
    - Lukosh, June, 1949; 1961 (Box 6)
    - Lundgren, Eric and Marion, 1939 (Box 6)
  - M
    - M (misc), 1 folder (Box 6)
    - McFee, Henry Lee, 1935 (Box 6)
    - Mallan, Lloyd, 1941; 1961 (Box 6)
    - Mandel, Estelle, 1951; 1956; See also Associated American Artists (Box 6)
    - Marsh, Reginald and Felicia, 1935; 1954 (Box 6)
    - Martyl, undated (Box 6)
    - Maryan, Hazel, 1958 (Box 6)
    - Massin, Eugene, 1950; 1951 (Box 6)
    - Massine, Leonide, 1942 (Box 6)
    - Mayer, Chester, 1951 (Box 6)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.), 1941-1950 (Box 6)
    - Milch Galleries (New York, N.Y.), 1939; 1957-1961 (Box 6)
    - Miller, George C., 1949 (Box 6)
    - Miller, Julius A., 1945 (Box 6)
    - Milwaukee Art Center, 1958-1961; undated (Box 6)
    - Milwaukee Art Institute, 1937; 1948-1950,; undated (Box 6)
    - Mount Mary College (Milwaukee, Wis.), 1957-1959 (Box 6)
    - Musick, Archie, undated (Box 6)
  - N
    - N (misc), 1 folder (Box 6)
    - Nash, Katherine, undated (Box 6)
    - National Academy of Design, 1950-1961; undated (Box 6)
    - [Elizabeth] Nelson Galleries (Chicago, Ill.), undated (Box 6)
    - New York World's Fair, 1939, 1938-1939 (Box 6)
    - North Shore Art League (Winnetka, Ill.), 1960-1961 (Box 6)
    - Northern Michigan College (Marquette, Mich.), 1953 (Box 6)
    - Nu-Art Engraving Company, 1951-1957 (Box 6)
    - Nutting, Myron, 1932 (Box 6)
  - O
    - O (misc), 1 folder (Box 6)
    - O'Brien's Art Emporium (Scottsdale, Ariz.), 1961-1963 (Box 6)
    - Oehlschlager, Frank J., 1950-1962; undated; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Ohio University, 1949-1954 (Box 6)
    - Ohio Wesleyan University, 1953-1954 (Box 6)
  - P
    - P (misc), 1 folder (Box 6)
    - Parnassus, 1940-1941 (Box 6)
    - Pearson, Ralph M., 1941 (Box 6)
    - Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, 1942-1943 (Box 6)
    - Pershing, Louise, 1944 (Box 6)
    - Philadelphia Art Alliance, 1942-1952 (Box 6)
    - Poor, Henry Varnum, 1935 (Box 6)
    - Poplack, William J. and Eleanor, 1955-1959; undated (Box 6)
    - Proxmire, William and Ellen, 1958-1959 (Box 7)
  - R
    - R (misc), 1 folder (Box 7)
    - [Frank K. M.] Rehn, Inc., 1935-1939 (Box 7)
    - Richard, Jack, 1955-1961 (Box 7)
    - Richardson, Constance, 1960 (Box 7)
    - Ripon College (Ripon, Wis.), 1958-1960 (Box 7)
    - Rittenberg, Henry R., 1956 (Box 7)
    - Robinson, Edward G., 1948 (Box 7)
    - [Increase] Robinson Gallery (Chicago, Ill.), 1933 (Box 7)
    - Rockford Art Association, 1942-1956 (Box 7)
    - Rosenberg, Samuel and Mrs., 1940; 1941 (Box 7)
    - Rowan, Edward B., See United States. Treasury Department
    - Russian War Relief, Inc., 1942 (Box 7)
  - S
    - S (misc), 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Salpeter, Harry, 1937; 1940 (Box 7)
    - Sample, Paul, 1960 (Box 7)
    - Schreiber, Georges, 1944-1960 (Box 7)
    - Schuyler, Remington, undated (Box 7)
    - Schwartz, William S. and Mona, 1942; 1950,; 1959 (Box 7)
    - Sepeshy, Zoltan, 1952-1957 (Box 7)
    - Shane, Frederick, 1941-1942; 1961 (Box 7)
    - Shannon, Charles, 1943 (Box 7)
    - Sheaffer, W. A., 1940-1941 (Box 7)
    - Shryock, Burnett H., 1938-1957; undated; See also Southern Illinois University (Box 7)
    - Simons, Hi, 1937-1942 (Box 7)
    - [Erik] Simonsen Art Agency (New York, N.Y.), 1956-1958; undated (Box 7)
    - Sivard, Robert, 1958 (Box 7)
    - Sloan, John, 1944 (Box 7)
    - Smith, Jacob Getlar, 1933-1935 (Box 7)
    - Smith, Lawrence Beall, 1942-1951 (Box 7)
    - Southern Illinois University, 1939-1952; see also Shryock, Burnett H. (Box 7)
    - Soyer, Raphael, 1939-1954; undated (Box 7)
    - Speicher, Eugene, 1936; undated (Box 7)
    - Stevens, Gross Studios, Inc. (Chicago, Ill.), 1952/1956; undated (Box 7)
    - Stites, Raymond S., 1936 (Box 7)
    - Swope Art Gallery (Terre Haute, Ind.), 1942-1943; undated (Box 7)
  - T
    - T (misc), 1 folder (Box 7)
    - Targ, William, 1944-1962 (Box 7)
    - Tash, Helene, 1956-1961; undated (Box 7)
    - Taubes, Frederic, undated (Box 7)
    - Tenney, Charles D., See Southern Illinois University
    - Thomas, Byron, 1944 (Box 7)
    - Time, 1951-1961 (Box 7)
    - Tracy, Elizabeth, 1940 (Box 7)
    - Trieglaff, Helen, See Parnassus
    - Truman, Harry S. (secretary), See Encyclopaedia Britannica
  - U
    - U (misc), 1 folder (Box 7)
    - United States. Public Buildings Administration, See United States. Treasury Department
    - United States. Treasury Department, 1935-1945 (Box 7)
    - United States. War Department, 1943-1946 (Box 7)
    - University of Illinois, 1934; 1956-1958 (Box 8)
    - University of Minnesota, 1938-1953 (Box 8)
    - University of Wisconsin, 1940-1962; undated (Box 8)
  - V
    - V (misc), 1 folder (Box 8)
    - [John H.] Vanderpoel Art Association, 1936 (Box 8)
    - Van Veen, Stuyvesant, undated (Box 8)
    - Varga, Margit, See Life
  - W
    - W (misc), 1 folder (Box 8)
    - Watson, Forbes, See United States. Treasury Department (Box 8)
    - Watson, Jean, 1961 (Box 8)
    - [Anna L.] Werbe Galleries (Detroit, Mich.), 1955-1956; undated (Box 8)
    - Werner, Nat, 1942 (Box 8)
    - Whitney Museum of American Art (New York, N.Y.), 1933-1946 (Box 8)
    - Wilson, Charles, 1941 (Box 8)
    - Wilson, Meredith, 1958 (Box 8)
    - Winsey, A. Reid, See DePauw University
    - Wisconsin Academy Review, 1954-1956 (Box 8)
    - Wisconsin Rural Artists Association, 1955-1961 (Box 8)
    - Wisconsin State College, 1949-1960 (Box 8)
    - Wood, Grant, 1935-1939; undated (Box 8)
    - World Publishing Company (Box 8)
  - Y-Z
    - Y-Z (misc), 1 folder (Box 8)
    - Zigrosser, Carl, 1933; 1940,; undated (Box 8)
    - Ziroli, Nicola, 1951; undated (Box 8)
    - Unidentified (Box 8)
- Artwork
  - Reproductions (Box 8)
  - Sketches, 3 items (Box 8)
- Writings
  - Articles (Box 8)
    manuscripts, published material
  - Books
    - A Pottery Sketchbook (Box 8)
    - "Notes on a Pottery Collaboration" - text (manuscript) (Box 8)
  - Critiques on paintings of other artists (Box 8)
  - Reviews (Box 8)
  - Speeches, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Statements on art (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
    World War II art projects for Life magazine - ms. drafts
- Memorabilia
  - Award (Box 8)
  - Clippings, 1943-1944; 1961,; undated (Box 8)
  - Exhibition catalogs, 1935-1948 (Box 8)
  - Leases (Box 8)
  - Lists of paintings with descriptions, some with prices, 2 items (Box 8)